<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The dressing up of the crown. In a sermon preached at St. Edmunds Bury in Suffolk, May 17. 1660. When His Majestie was there solemnly proclaimed King of England, &amp;c. By Laurence Womock.</title>
            <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96832</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3342</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1029_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208908</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867825</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867825</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168884</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96832)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168884)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 152:E1029[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The dressing up of the crown. In a sermon preached at St. Edmunds Bury in Suffolk, May 17. 1660. When His Majestie was there solemnly proclaimed King of England, &amp;c. By Laurence Womock.</title>
                  <author>Womock, Laurence, 1612-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by W.H. for Will. Sheares at the blew Bible in Bedford street in Covent Garden,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1660]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The final leaf contains two lines of errata.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 17, 1660".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168884:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Dreſſing up OF THE CROWN. IN A SERMON Preached at S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Edmunds Bury</hi> in <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folk,</hi> May 17. 1660. WHEN His <hi>MAJESTIE</hi> was there ſolemnly proclaimed KING of <hi>ENGLAND, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By LAURENCE WOMOCK.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Pſal. 45. 1.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſpeak of the things, which I have made touching the King.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>W. H.</hi> for <hi>Will. Sheares</hi> at the blew Bible in <hi>Bedford ſtreet</hi> in <hi>Covent Garden.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:168884:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168884:2"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Dreſſing up of the</hi> CROWN</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 132. verſ. 18. the later part of the verſe.</bibl>
               <q>But upon himſelf ſhall his Crown flouriſh.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He end of this Convention is, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim the Authority of his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty over us, and to profeſs our duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſubjection to it. But, will our <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks</hi> ſay, why ſhould we trouble our ſelves about a Magiſtrate? The Apoſtle doth adviſe us not <hi>to be the ſervants of men</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 2 3.</note>: and he ſaith, <hi>the Law is not made for the righteous</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Tim. 1. 9.</note>; and if the Prince makes any civil <hi>Sanction,</hi> it muſt not be adopted into the Law of Faith, and therefore it is <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> void and of none effect; for <hi>whatſoever is not of faith is ſin</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 14 23.</note>. Beſides, <hi>compulſion</hi> cannot bring the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to conformity, and <hi>capital</hi> puniſhments are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere, cruel and unchriſtian; for they do not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive the <hi>Malefactor</hi> of his life, but of his time too, and ſo haply prevent him of ſome miracle of providence, which otherwiſe might have led him to repentance.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168884:3"/> And for theſe conſiderations, ſay theſe men, why ſhould we give our ſelves the temptation of ſetting up a King over us.</p>
            <p>But theſe Objections carry their confutation upon their forehead; &amp; were there nothing elſe to be ſaid, it is ſufficient to evacuate their force, that theſe very Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectors, when ever they gain their opportunity, do not only practiſe the ſame things themſelves, which they now condemn in their Superiours, but alſo act beyond them. When it becomes their own concern, they can plead neceſſity, and find reaſons, and interpret theſe very Scriptures in favour of themſelves, and alledge o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in juſtification of their proceedings; which will evince, to any diſcerning judgment, that the deſign of theſe men, in pulling the Crown from off the head, and wreſting the Sword and Scepter out of the hands of others, is but to gain an advantage to take them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their own poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>What I repreſent in this diſcourſe, is but an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <hi>Copy</hi> of that which we have ſeen drawn out to the life before our eyes.</p>
            <p>For the carrying on of which atchievement, Good God! what adulation and flattery, what diſſimulation and hypocriſie hath been uſed! what horrid perjuries, abuſive invocations, profane mockeries, execrable blaſphemies have been put upon Almighty God! what jugling colluſion, villanous cheats, deviliſh treacheries have been practiſed upon the Lords Anointed! At laſt they laid his ſacred Body in the duſt (though they could never lay his Honour there) to be as a ſtepping ſtone to advance ambitious <hi>Treaſon</hi> to the Throne. But bleſſed be our good God, who is as well a God of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice as of Patience; who hath not ſuffered the glorious light of our eyes to be always eclipſed, nor the deſigns of that bloody <hi>Inſolent</hi> to take root for ever, but hath blaſted them when they ſeemed to be almoſt full
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168884:3"/> bloom'd, not permiting them to bring forth any fruit to maturity; and hath caſt confuſion upon the Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and Triumphs of thoſe Uſurpations, and by a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful hand of providence, hath vouchſafed to reſtore the moſt <hi>excellent Majeſty</hi> of the Son, to the Scepter of that power, and the ſplendor of that glory, that had been raviſhed from the hand of that <hi>bleſsed Father.</hi> So that what was calculated for the Family and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of that <hi>David</hi> mentioned in the two laſt verſes of this <hi>Pſalm,</hi> may ſerve the ends of our diſcourſe, as if they had been a prediction of the Family and Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors of <hi>Ours,</hi> in their Dominion over us. <hi>There will I make the Horn of David to bud, I have ordained a lamp for mine anointed. His enemies will I cloath with ſhame: but upon himſelf ſhall his Crown flouriſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe words are a repreſentment of the Power and Majeſty <hi>Royal,</hi> in its continuance and amplification. And, bleſſed be God! how wonderfully doth the <hi>horn</hi> of that power ſprout and grow up amongſt us! what gladſome rayes of light, of joy and glory doth the <hi>lamp</hi> of that Majeſty diſplay upon us, at a diſtance, even to the envy and amazement of the enemies. But for <hi>them</hi> ſince the fatherly affection of our moſt <hi>gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign</hi> is pleaſed, upon their ſubmiſſion, to vouchſafe them a better Livery, a Livery of his own Royal fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and grace, I ſhall not exaſperate any paſſion to cut out and make up the garment of <hi>ſhame</hi> for them; and yet I muſt add this, That I have no protection for them from the ſeverity of a Divine vengeance, except they repent. If they repent not, God will take the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice into his own hands; for he ſaith, <hi>His enemies will I cloath with ſhame.</hi> The next words are my <hi>Theame</hi> this day, <hi>[Upon Himſelf ſhall his Crown flouriſh.]</hi> Wherein I muſt firſt handle the <hi>Crown,</hi> and make ſome reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the <hi>Owner,</hi> the <hi>Sacred Perſon</hi> whoſe Crown it is; and then proceed to ſhew you how you are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:168884:4"/> to <hi>ſupport,</hi> and <hi>adorn,</hi> and <hi>dreſs it up</hi> to make it <hi>flouriſh;</hi> and laſtly, I ſhall acquaint you with thoſe great bleſſings and advantages that will accrew to you by the influences thereof; for this <hi>[Himſelf]</hi> is of a very diffuſive nature, and is vertually extended over all the body of the <hi>people;</hi> And this Crown ſet upon the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigns head, the more it <hi>flouriſheth</hi> there, the greater refreſhment, the more bleſſings will you all receive from the ſhadow of it.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>I. <hi>Of the Crown firſt.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And this we muſt handle under a threefold notion.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As a repreſentation of the Divine Ordinance or inſtitution of <hi>Government</hi> in general.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As the higheſt Enſign of Authority, the peculiar ornament of <hi>Monarchy;</hi> and ſo we muſt conſider it as having the <hi>Supremacy</hi> or <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> which is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt excellency of Power and Dominion lodged in it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As a peculiar inſtrument of a <hi>Monarch,</hi> diſtinct from the <hi>Sword;</hi> for 'tis not the <hi>Sword</hi> that ſhall flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; that would bring but little eaſe, little content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to a Nation under the triumphs of it. 'Tis the <hi>Crown</hi> ſhall flouriſh.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>1.</head>
                  <p>Of which as it repreſents the Divine Inſtitution or Ordinance of <hi>Government</hi> in general; For God hath ſet up a kind of <hi>Authority,</hi> that is, an Order of <hi>Rule</hi> in univerſal nature, even in the pureſt conſtitution of it. We may obſerve this in all the ſeveral parts of the world. Amongſt <hi>Inanimates</hi> there is a <hi>first mover</hi> that carries about all the other Orbs of Heaven; and in the Heaven there is a <hi>Sun</hi> to rule the day, a <hi>Moon</hi> and the <hi>Stars</hi> to govern the night; and the influences of thoſe Superior bodies have a great ſway over all <hi>ſublunary</hi>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:168884:4"/> Creatures, and their operations. If we look into the world of <hi>Animals,</hi> we ſhall find a certain kind of <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination</hi> amongſt them. A <hi>King</hi> amongſt the <hi>Beaſts;</hi> a <hi>Queen</hi> amongſt the <hi>Birds;</hi> ſome excellency is ſtampt upon them by the <hi>Royal Soveraign</hi> of the world, to which the reſt of each kind do ſtoop and yield obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance.</p>
                  <p>In the world of <hi>Rational</hi> Creatures we may obſerve the ſame method of <hi>ſuperiority</hi> &amp; <hi>ſubordination.</hi> There are ſeveral Orders of <hi>Angels,</hi> and the <hi>Schoolmen</hi> tell us, that thoſe of an higher <hi>Order</hi> do communicate light and knowledge to ſuch as are inferiour; and we finde they have their ſeveral <hi>Provinces</hi> over which they do <hi>preſide,</hi> in the 10. and 12. Chapters of <hi>Daniel.</hi> There is order and ſubordination even in <hi>Hell</hi> it ſelf; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it would be a worſe Hell than it is, if there were not a <hi>Prince</hi> of <hi>Devils</hi> to rule over it.</p>
                  <p>If we look into our own <hi>Bodies,</hi> we ſee the <hi>head</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rives the ſenſe and motion into all the parts and organs; and in the <hi>Soul,</hi> we have the <hi>Will,</hi> that <hi>rational</hi> appetite to direct and command all the Members and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. And thus it ſhould be in the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State;</hi> wherein the Commands and Orders ſhould iſſue from the <hi>Head,</hi> where the excellency of power is chiefly lodged, and from thence they ſhould be regularly trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the reſt of the Body.</p>
                  <p>God gives a bleſſing to ſuch a Conſtitution, and to the people that lives under it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 99. 6. <hi>Moſes and Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron amongſt his Saints, and Samuel among ſuch as call up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his name. Theſe called upon the Lord and he heard them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Without this all the bands of <hi>Society</hi> are diſſolved; the people without it are like a flock of ſcattered <note place="margin">1 King. 22 17. Zac. 13. 7.</note> ſheep (which indeed are not a flock) without a ſhep herd. And when this Order is perverted, when the power and authority runs not in the proper channel: when commands are not iſſued forth from the Head
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168884:5"/> and Fountain, but uſurped and inforced by inferiours without and againſt, <hi>Them;</hi> this the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> delivers for a ſore infliction, a heavy judgment upon a people. This was a great exorbitancy and eye-ſoar to the wiſeſt <hi>Solomon,</hi> To ſee <hi>folly ſet in great dignity, ſervants upon</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 10. 6, 7.</note> 
                     <hi>Horſes, and Princes walking as ſervants upon the earth.</hi> It is a huge undecency, not ſeemly for <hi>a ſervant to rule over Princes, Prov.</hi> 19. 10. 'Tis <hi>Moleſtum</hi> too, an exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy, that will diſquiet the whole land, 'tis ſo intolle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. <hi>For three things the earth is diſquieted, and for four, which it cannot bear. For a ſervant when he reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</hi> That's the firſt, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 21, 22. This is not the <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance</hi> of God, but his judgment upon a people; and ſo 'tis threatned (therefore not a bleſſing, but a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) <hi>Iſay</hi> 3. When God takes away the <hi>Iudge</hi> and the <hi>Prophet,</hi> and the <hi>Prudent,</hi> and the <hi>Honourable</hi> man, and ſuffers <hi>Children</hi> to be their <hi>Princes,</hi> Children in <hi>knowledge</hi> and <hi>experience</hi> (though otherwiſe old e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough) and <hi>Babes</hi> to rule over them; <hi>The people ſhall be oppreſſed every one by another, and every one by his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; the child ſhall behave himſelf proudly againſt the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, and the baſe againſt the Honourable: and Women</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">See the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riginal. verſ. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>ſhall rule over them, and they that can beſt flatter them and call them bleſſed,</hi> ſhall lead them firſt into <hi>error,</hi> and then into <hi>destruction,</hi> verſe 2, 3, 4, 5. with the 12. And if you will not for all this believe it to be a judgment, though ſwallowed up by ſuch as call you <hi>bleſſed</hi> (as if there were a happineſs in being ruined by ſuch Inſtruments) hear the complaints of thoſe that groaned under ſuch a judgement, and obſerve the effects of it in their exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; <hi>The Crown is fallen from our head, wo unto us that we have ſinned, Lam.</hi> 5. 16. If the <hi>Crown</hi> falls from the head, wherever it lights 'tis woful; and therefore the Church proceeds in her complaint, <hi>Servants have ruled over us: there is none that doth deliver us out of their hand. Princes</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">verſ. 8. verſ. 12.</note> 
                     <hi>are hanged up by their hand: the faces of the Elders were not honoured.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:168884:5"/>
                  <p> When men ſhall <hi>Canonize</hi> themſelves, or paſs an Act for their own <hi>Saintſhip,</hi> and then preſume (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding their <hi>oaths,</hi> &amp; bounden duty to the contrary) <hi>to bind their Kings in chains, and their Nobles with fetters of iron,</hi> and cut off their heads, and ſay, <hi>ſuch honour have all the Saints;</hi> and to palliate the crime, abuſe and profane the <hi>ſacred</hi> Text, which is reſt rained to one pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar proceſs of affairs under Gods own <hi>immediate</hi> conduct and direction; For <hi>Moſes</hi> was but Gods <hi>Lieutenant</hi> in the management of that expedition, and received his particular orders from his own hand; and upon this account, the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> tells us, This was to <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the judgment that was written, Pſal.</hi> 149. laſt. If men will make uſe of ſuch actions for precedents, as were never ſet or intended for their imitation, caſting behind their backs Gods expreſs commands, which were given to be the ſtanding meaſures of their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; This is a very ſad ſtrain for the Church of God to daunce after.</p>
                  <p>When the fire out of the <hi>Bramble</hi> ſhall devour the lofty <hi>Cedars,</hi> as in <hi>Jothams</hi> parable, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 9. when the <hi>luſts that war in the Members ſhall overtop the head,</hi> and <hi>preſcribe to reaſon,</hi> and <hi>rebel againſt the law of the mind;</hi> All good ſouls, in this caſe are concerned to take up that complaint, <hi>Lam.</hi> 5. 17. <hi>For this our heart is faint; for theſe things our eyes are dim.</hi> We ought then to mourn, foraſmuch as it is evident, that ſin hath provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked God to anger, and <hi>that</hi> ſin, and <hi>that</hi> anger together, have diſturbed the <hi>regular</hi> method, order, and conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the world, which conſiſted of <hi>ſubjection</hi> and <hi>ſuperiority;</hi> and this is that which the <hi>Crown</hi> betoken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and is the ſumme of our firſt <hi>Reflection</hi> upon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:168884:6"/>
                  <head>2.</head>
                  <p>But we muſt reflect upon it as the <hi>higheſt</hi> enſign of <hi>Authority,</hi> the peculiar ornament of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> having the <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Soveraignty,</hi> that is, the greateſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of Power and Dominion lodged in it. And ſo we may conſider that it comes from a word, which ſignifies to <hi>ſeparate</hi> and <hi>conſecrate;</hi> and conſequently 'tis a thing <hi>ſacred,</hi> and renders the perſon <hi>ſuch</hi> that wears it.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>form</hi> of Government commenced with the world in <hi>Adam,</hi> who was the <hi>first-born</hi> (as it were) of all mankind, and ſo it commenced upon the account of <hi>primageniture.</hi> Neither was this <hi>prerogative</hi> loſt by <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam's</hi> fall, either to himſelf or his firſt begotten; For we ſee it deſcended upon <hi>Cain,</hi> and is aſſerted to him by God himſelf, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. 7. And long after we find it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged by <hi>Iacob</hi> in his firſt-born <hi>Ruben,</hi> Gen. 49. 3, 4. <hi>Ruben, thou art my first-born, my might, and the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of my ſtrength, the excellency of dignity, and the excellency of power.</hi> And it was this <hi>prerogative</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advantages that made <hi>Iacob</hi> ſo ambitious of the birth-right. And though upon the diviſion and diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of families for peopling the world, there was a kind of neceſſity to alter this Conſtitution in this cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance of Perſon; yet the <hi>Form</hi> it ſelf (of <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy)</hi> continued, and as far as my obſervation reacheth, it was the only Government that was exerciſed in the firſt ages all the world over; which argues it was gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally taken up, upon the authority of ſome <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> unqueſtionable principle.</p>
                  <p>And although this were interrupted amongſt the people and Church of God, while they ſojourned in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and after their Redemption too, for a ſeaſon, when God took them by a ſpecial providence, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168884:6"/> them under the wings of his <hi>own</hi> immediate juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction; yet even in his own Law, he was pleaſed to make an early proviſion for the reſtitution of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, when they came to a ſettlement in <hi>Canaan,</hi> Deut. 27. 14. And though there were ſome miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age in the management, ſome inordination in their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of a <hi>King,</hi> yet was God pleaſed to <hi>ſign</hi> the <hi>Grant,</hi> and <hi>own</hi> the conſtitution, and <hi>appoint</hi> a ſpecial <hi>Rite</hi> of Unction for the conſecration of <hi>Sauls</hi> perſon to that office, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8. And therefore what is ſaid by the Lord, <hi>[I gave them a King in mine anger,] Heſ.</hi> 13. 11. is not to be underſtood of <hi>Saul;</hi> for 'tis evident to me, that God gave him to that people out of <hi>Compaſsion,</hi> and at their <hi>cry,</hi> and deſigned him the inſtrument, to <hi>ſave them from the Philiſtines,</hi> 1 Sam. 9. 16. And to this end God pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out his Spirit upon him, and gave him <hi>another heart,</hi> a heart fit for <hi>Government,</hi> 1 Sam. 10. 9, 10. And had he had the patience to wait upon God, ſome few hours longer, till <hi>Samuel's</hi> coming to <hi>Gilgal</hi> to offer the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, the Lord had eſtabliſhed his Kingdom upon <hi>Iſrael</hi> for ever, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 13. 13. And if we conſider how <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> aggravates his ingratitude upon this account, we cannot conclude that God made him King out of <hi>anger;</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15. 17.</note> no anger I am confident, againſt <hi>Saul</hi> at that time in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his <hi>Perſon,</hi> or his <hi>ſettlement</hi> in that <hi>Royal</hi> office.</p>
                  <p>To put the matter out of all queſtion, <hi>David</hi> was a King too, yet certainly he was not given to that people out of <hi>anger;</hi> for the Lord ſaith, <hi>I have choſen David</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 89. 20</note> 
                     <hi>my ſervant, with my holy oyl have I anointed him, &amp;c.</hi> Pſal. 89. 20. And the advancement of that people unto a <hi>Monarchy,</hi> was ſuch an <hi>exaltation</hi> of State and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to the whole <hi>Nation,</hi> that God upbraids their ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, as being heightned upon this very ſcore, that God had ſet a <hi>beautiful Crown upon their head, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpered them into a Kingdom,</hi> Ezek. 16. 12, 13.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:168884:7"/>
                  <p> And the truth is, the wiſeſt States-men do conclude <hi>Monarchical</hi> Government; A threefold advantage we may obſerve it hath, above States more <hi>popular;</hi> 'Tis more <hi>eaſie,</hi> more <hi>potent,</hi> more <hi>honourable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. More <hi>eaſie;</hi> This is evident in ſhort; for where there are more men, there are more luſts and paſsions to command, more appetites and intereſts to be grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; and this muſt needs evince their Government, in the general to be more difficult.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. As <hi>Monarchy</hi> is more <hi>eaſie,</hi> ſo 'tis more <hi>ſtrong</hi> and <hi>potent;</hi> becauſe (beſides the advantages of <hi>ſecrecy,</hi> which can never be ſo firmly ſealed, when deſigns are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated to a multitude.) A <hi>Monarchy</hi> is leſs ſubject to <hi>diviſions;</hi> and leſs ſubject to <hi>diviſions</hi> it muſt needs be, becauſe 'tis more reduced to <hi>unitie</hi> in one ſingle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the <hi>Prince.</hi> Hereupon we ſee all bodies <hi>Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> that they may be the more <hi>united</hi> and <hi>potent,</hi> are governed after this <hi>Form,</hi> under the command of one chief General.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. As more Potent ſo more <hi>Honourable;</hi> becauſe the ſplend or and glory is all contracted, as it were, into one <hi>centre,</hi> and ſo carries the figure of Gods own <hi>Supream Majeſtie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For when the Almighty is pleaſed to ſet forth his own <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Creatneſs,</hi> he does not aſſume the Title of <hi>MAGISTRATE,</hi> nor call himſelf by the name of <hi>Senator</hi> or <hi>Protector;</hi> Theſe are creatures of too low a ſtature to be his <hi>Repreſentativs:</hi> But he cloaths himſelf in the <hi>Royal apparrel,</hi> and makes choice of the ſign of the <hi>Crown,</hi> as the fitteſt for his Majeſty to appear in. He is <hi>King of Kings and Lord of Lords,</hi> and this <hi>name</hi> and <hi>title</hi> is that which we find ingraven, not only upon <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 15.</note> the <hi>Veſture,</hi> but alſo upon the very <hi>Thigh</hi> of Chriſt, as if theſe were a production that iſſued from his very <hi>loins,</hi> Rev. 19. 16. And if you pleaſe to take the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168884:7"/> the holy Ghoſt in Scripture hath remarked it, as the greateſt honour the Father could do to Chriſt, and the greateſt bleſſing he could confer upon his Church, that he would raiſe up Kings <hi>to ſerve him and ſuccour her. All Kings ſhall fall down before thee,</hi> as is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed unto Chriſt, Pſal. 72. 10, 11. <hi>And Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fathers,</hi> as is promiſed to the Church, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 23.</p>
                  <p>And indeed we may obſerve, that God repoſeth a very great truſt in Princes, for the ſupport and advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his worſhip. When he was about to build the <hi>Tabernacle</hi> for his own ſervice and glory, the <hi>model</hi> of it was not given to the heady <hi>multitude,</hi> nor yet to <hi>Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron</hi> the Prieſt, but to the Prince, to <hi>Moſes,</hi> his own immediate Miniſter, <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. 9. And when he was pleaſed to have his worſhip fixed, the pattern of the <hi>Temple</hi> that he will be honoured in, is given to <hi>David,</hi> to the King, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28. 17, 19. The Prince is <hi>Cuſtos utri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſque tabulae,</hi> God hath committed the care of his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and ſervice to his inſpection, the Holy <hi>Bible</hi> to his cuſtody, not finding a ſafer place than the <hi>Crown</hi> to lodge it in. The Tables of the Law are depoſited in the hands of <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 34. 31, &amp;c. And the Book of the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> was wont to be delivered into the hands of the <hi>King</hi> at his <hi>Coronation;</hi> and this was according to Gods own preſcription, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 18, 19, 20. where <note place="margin">2 Chron. 23. 11.</note> the King is directed to tranſcribe a Copy of the Law, and to peruſe and ſtudy it for his inſtruction; and ever ſince <hi>Defenſor Fidei,</hi> Defender of the Faith, hath been a Title due to all religious Princes.</p>
                  <p>The office of a King then is no way inconſiſtent with the priviledge of a child of God: He may very faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully ſerve God in that high calling; For I do not find that God doth <hi>depoſe</hi> Princes, or preſcribe them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce their Function, when he invites them to adore
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168884:8"/> and worſhip Chriſt: <hi>Be wiſe now therefore, O ye Kings, ſerve the Lord with fear, and kiſs the Son left he be angry.</hi> That is all we find them exhorted to, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. 10, 11, 12. Nay even to ſuch, as are (mentioned in that Pſalm, to be) in a confederacy againſt Chriſt, to ſuch, I ſay, doth the Holy Ghoſt reſerve the reverence of their <hi>Titles.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> enjoynes us <hi>to pray for them:</hi> Saint <hi>Peter, to ſubmit our ſelves unto them,</hi> under this conſideration, that <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 1, 2. 1 Pet. 2. 13.</note> they are inveſted with ſuch an Authority.</p>
                  <p>But ſome of Saint <hi>Peters</hi> pretended Succeſſors are ſo far from following his example, that they take liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (at their pleaſure) to transform Princes in to Tyrants, and that they may ſpoil them of their Kingdoms, they alienate the hearts and affections of their Subjects and abſolve them from their Allegiance. But obſerve the cunning of their practices: They allow not Subjects to withdraw their obedience or duty from their Prince, by no means; that were againſt a <hi>divine Right,</hi> an execrable injuſtice; but to free the Subject from ſuch a guilt, the <hi>Pope</hi> unkings the perſon of the Prince, and then the people, no longer owes him duty; Thus the Cardinal inſtructs the people, as the <hi>Popes</hi> Curate, <hi>Non permitto, ut Regi non pareas, quod eſſet contra jus</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Bellar. Cont. Bar. cap. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>Divinum; ſed facio, ut qui tibi Rex erat, non ſit deinceps tibi Rex. Regi rejecto Vicarius Chriſti obedientiam exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri prohibet.</hi> But Chriſt hath ſurrogated no <hi>Officer</hi> in his Church to practiſe ſuch black Arts, or exerciſe ſuch a <hi>Vicarious</hi> power for the advancement of his Kingdom; nor will he acknowledge ſuch Inſtruments to be his, but rather the Devils Vicars, whoſe uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and arrogance they imitate. And I wiſh ſome of thoſe that do pretend to <hi>Reformation,</hi> did not juſtifie the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this particular: for I muſt do them that juſtice, I find the more ingenuous amongſt them, at leaſt if we may believe them, do diſclaim ſuch
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168884:8"/> Doctrines, and abominate the practiſe.</p>
                  <p>There is ſuch a vicinity, ſuch a relation betwixt God and the King, that commonly they are ſerved and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obeyed together. If you read of an Inſurrection, <hi>'tis</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>againſt the Lord, as well as againſt his Anointed.</hi> In <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> time, thoſe who did <hi>blaſpheme God,</hi> did <hi>ſlander the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 89. 50 Edit. Lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turg.</note> 
                     <hi>foot-ſteps of his Anointed</hi> alſo. And in <hi>Iſaiahs</hi> time, thoſe who bade defiance to their <hi>Prince,</hi> did at laſt fly as high as there was any <hi>Majeſty</hi> to be affronted, they ſpit their poyſon in the face of Heaven it ſelf, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 21. And how is it poſſible, but the diſhonour put upon the King, ſhould reflect upon God himſelf? For the King is a <hi>Coin</hi> of Gods own impreſſion and ſtamping: He ſaith, <hi>By me Kings reign:</hi> and <hi>I have ſaid, ye are gods.</hi> The <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pro.</hi> 8. 15. Pſal. 82. 6.</note> Prince hath <hi>Gods image</hi> and <hi>ſuperſcription</hi> ingraven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. Indeed his <hi>Majeſty</hi> is the only viſible image that God hath ſet up of himſelf to be worſhipped: and yet I would not have you turn your Prince into an <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol,</hi> but to perform what you find enjoyned by Chriſt and the Holy Ghoſt, and the Apoſtles in Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Render unto Ceſar the things that are Ceſars,</hi> ſaith <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 21 Prov. 24. 21. 1 Pet. 2. 17</note> our Saviour: <hi>Fear thou the Lord and the King,</hi> ſaith <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon, Fear God and honour the King,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Peter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſuppoſe the King will not comply in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation and ſettlement of <hi>Religion.</hi> Why, if we ſpeak of <hi>Reformation,</hi> the queſtion will be, who is fitteſt to judge, as having the beſt aſſiſtance and advantages to diſcern what is fit to be reformed. In the great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> addreſs themſelves thus unto the <hi>Emperour</hi> for ſettlement of Religion, <hi>Supplicamus veſtrae Majeſtati, ut fidem immotam cuſtodire ſanciatis:</hi> They ſupplicate, but have no Commiſſion from their great Maſter Chriſt <hi>to levy war,</hi> and put a <hi>force</hi> upon their <hi>Soveraign.</hi> In this caſe the Church of God is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed no other weapons, but <hi>Preces &amp; lacrymae,</hi> prayers
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168884:9"/> and tears. <hi>Defendenda Religio est à privatis omnibus, non occidendo ſed mortendo, non ſaevitia ſed patientia, non ſce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere ſed</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Lib. 5. c. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>fide,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lactantius;</hi> Religion is to be defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by all private perſons, by laying down their own lives, not by attempting the lives of others, not by cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, but by patience; not by treachery, but by a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and innocent profeſsion of the Faith. Thus did the bleſſed ſervants of God, this was their faith and practiſe in all the pureſt ages of the Church; <hi>They lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Revel. 12. 11. chap. 6. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>not their lives unto the death; but were ſlain for the word of God, and for the Teſtimony which they held.</hi> And in this caſe, is it not enough, that the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>If we ſuffer with Chriſt, we ſhall alſo reign with him:</hi> adding withal, <hi>That if we deny him, he will alſo deny us.</hi> And tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> it is a very great degree of our <hi>denial</hi> of him, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to bear this part of his <hi>Croſs,</hi> when his wiſedome and providence ſhall think fit to impoſe it upon us; when to ſhift it off our ſelves, we lay it upon the ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of our <hi>Soveraign,</hi> whoſe <hi>Crown</hi> entitles him to a <hi>Supremacy</hi> of command, but does not inthral him in a <hi>ſubjection</hi> to the people. And thus you have my refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xion upon the <hi>Crown,</hi> in the ſecond notion of it, as it is the <hi>Enſign</hi> and <hi>Ornament</hi> of <hi>Monarchy.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>3.</head>
                  <p>I muſt make a third reflexion upon it (though it be a very brief one) as it is diſtinguiſhed from other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments, that have relation to the <hi>Royal Office,</hi> the <hi>Scepter</hi> and the <hi>Sword;</hi> for all theſe three, the <hi>Crown,</hi> the <hi>Sword,</hi> the <hi>Scepter,</hi> are the Inſtruments of a King, to which we owe reſpective duties. The <hi>Scepter</hi> (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes ſuppoſed to be a <hi>juſt and</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">For the King can do no wrong.</note> 
                     <hi>right Scepter)</hi> muſt meaſure our actions; to that therefore we owe obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And becauſe the King <hi>bears not the Sword in vain;</hi> therefore to the <hi>Sword</hi> we owe <hi>fear.</hi> And becauſe the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168884:9"/> 
                     <hi>Crown</hi> entitles the perſon that wears it unto <hi>Majeſty,</hi> it requires of <hi>veneration,</hi> we muſt therefore pay <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> to it.</p>
                  <p>If this had been ſuch a prediction, as we find that touching <hi>Hazael</hi> (which put the great Prophet into a bitter paſſion of weeping to utter it) 2 <hi>King.</hi> 8. 12. That his <hi>Sword ſhould flouriſh in his hand,</hi> and be <hi>bathed in</hi> your <hi>heart-blood,</hi> that it ſhould triumph in the <hi>ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of your innocent Babes, and in <hi>ripping</hi> up your wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men great with child, and other bloody outrages: This had been very dreadful (how juſt ſoever in the eyes of Heaven) to you. But we have a God of mercy, and his <hi>Vicegerent</hi> reſembles him in this vertue. The King of our <hi>Iſrael</hi> is a very <hi>merciful</hi> King; if by any graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous conceſſions, his Majeſty can poſſibly ptevent it, he deſires not to have his <hi>Sword</hi> (amongſt his own Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects) but his <hi>Crown</hi> to flouriſh.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>II. <hi>The ſecond General Part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>But how is this to be accompliſhed? That ſhal be our next enquiry. Without queſtion 'tis our duty to do ſomething to this effect: 'Tis not to be expected, that all ſhould come <hi>immediately</hi> from Heaven, and the hand of God. Here is a bleſſing from Heaven inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Text, <hi>[It ſhall flouriſh,]</hi> and Divine provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence doth offer fair to make it good: But we are concerned, 'tis our bounden duty to contribute our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours, and uſe all the beſt means we can to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh it.</p>
               <p>That the <hi>Crown</hi> then may flouriſh, we are obliged to do two things; 1. <hi>To water it.</hi> 2. <hi>To dreſs it up.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>1. <hi>To water it,</hi> with our <hi>Prayers,</hi> with our <hi>Tears,</hi> with our <hi>Eſtates</hi> and <hi>Fortunes,</hi> with our <hi>Lives</hi> and deareſt <hi>Blood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:168884:10"/> 1. <hi>With our prayers.</hi> This is a prime duty charged upon us by Apoſtolical Authority, 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1, 2. <hi>I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort firſt of all, that ſupplication, prayers, interceſſions be made for all men: For Kings, and for all that be in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</hi> And the twentieth Pſalm is an excellent prayer penn'd to this purpoſe. But therein we find none of thoſe <hi>perverſe inſinuations,</hi> which ſome men inſert into their ſupplications for their Princes; they have their ſeditious <hi>Iſ'es,</hi> and ſcandalous <hi>Proviſo'es; If God hath reſerved any mercy in ſtore for him and his Family.</hi> Theſe are dangerous <hi>inſertions,</hi> and leave very ill impreſſions upon mens minds, as if their Princes Title were ſtill queſtionable in Heaven, when 'tis moſt clearly aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on earth, and vindicated by all the Laws of God and man.</p>
               <p>And I am jealous, though other things have been pretended, that one main reaſon why the <hi>Liturgy</hi> of the Church was laid aſide, was, becauſe the Prayers therein, for the proſperity of the <hi>Kings Majeſty,</hi> were ſo clear a contradiction to ſome mens intendments, and ſo too apt to give a check to their after-horrid practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes againſt him. Which practiſes have invited and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged all Loyal Subjects to <hi>water</hi> his Crown with their Tears, in order to its reflouriſhing. And,</p>
               <p n="2">2. This is the next way of <hi>watering</hi> it. And thus was that Crown watered by the tears both of Prince and people, when it was invaded by that ſeditious flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er <hi>Abſolom,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 30. <hi>And David went up by the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent of Mount Olivet and wept as he went up, and had his head covered, and he went barefoot, and all the people that was with him covered every man his head, and they went up, weeping as they went up.</hi> And to my knowledge our Engliſh Crown hath many a time, under our late ſad Revolutions, been thus <hi>watered.</hi> But it was thrown down ſo <hi>low</hi> in the duſt, and trampled ſo <hi>deep</hi> in the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168884:10"/> mire, and the <hi>earth of ſeditious people</hi> grown ſo ſtiff and hardened over it, that had it not been wonderfully <hi>wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered</hi> with ſhowers of bleſſings <hi>from Heaven,</hi> ſomented and cheriſhed by ſacred influences from <hi>above,</hi> it could not have viſited the world with ſuch a glorious and comfortable <hi>Reſurrection;</hi> for which we have as juſt cauſe to <hi>water</hi> it now with <hi>tears</hi> of <hi>joy,</hi> as before with tears of <hi>ſorrow</hi> and lamentation.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But prayers and tears coſt us little, (though ſome men will not afford their Soveraigns Crown ſuch a Subſidy.) You muſt water it with your Eſtates too, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 5, 6, 7. <hi>For this cauſe pay ye Tribute,</hi> and <hi>render unto every one his due, tribute to whom tribute is due;</hi> 'Tis <hi>debitum,</hi> a due debt, and that <hi>for conſcience ſake.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If the Laws of the Land have ſet bounds to the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects Contributions of this kind; 'tis not my concern to cancel them; but the needs of the Crown muſt be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, the charges defrayed, the State and Grandeur of it ſupported. We muſt ſhare in the burden, if we would ſhare in the honour and benefit; and unleſs we do ſupport it, it cannot protect us. Neither</p>
               <p n="4">4. Can it in every juncture of time <hi>flouriſh</hi> to this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of <hi>protection,</hi> unleſs we water it, as occaſion ſerve, with our <hi>blood</hi> alſo. And this is a duty incumbent upon us, and that in regard of the <hi>Oath</hi> of God. We are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 8. 2.</note> to maintain His Majeſties <hi>Crown and Dignity</hi> with our lives as well as with our Fortunes. And thoſe loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Subjects of <hi>David</hi> did not think their blood too dear to water his Crown, when they thought him worth <hi>ten thouſand,</hi> and yet would not conſent, that he ſhould <hi>hazard his ſacred Perſon in the battel,</hi> for fear he ſhould <note place="margin">2 Sam. 18. 3. &amp;c. 21. 17.</note> miſcarry in the adventure, and ſo <hi>quench the light of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael.</hi> All the loyal blood, that is ſhed in the juſt quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel of the <hi>Crown,</hi> will be congealed and turned into Jewels to dreſs it up; and if it ſhould not prove ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:168884:11"/> (in all eſſayes) to this effect, yet mixt with other virtues, it would contribute to the <hi>dreſſing</hi> up of a more glorious Crown for Majeſty and Loyaltie in Heaven. And thus you hear how the Crown is to be <hi>watered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. But this is not the <hi>All</hi> of a loyal Subjects duty. The <hi>Crown</hi> is as well to be <hi>drest up,</hi> as to be <hi>watered,</hi> to make it <hi>flouriſh.</hi> Dreſt up with <hi>lauds</hi> and <hi>acclamations</hi> to the perſon of the <hi>Prince;</hi> dreſt up with <hi>praiſes</hi> and <hi>thankſgivings</hi> to Almighty God for him; dreſt up with an honourable <hi>Militia</hi> to adorn and guard it; dreſt up with a prompt and chearful <hi>obedience</hi> to ſerve its inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Dreſt up with <hi>Lauds</hi> and <hi>Acclamations</hi> to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Prince, we muſt ſing a joyful <hi>Hoſanna</hi> to our Son of <hi>David.</hi> At his Coronation the Trumpets ſounded, and the people ſhouted, <hi>God ſave King Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> 1 King. 1. 39. How did <hi>Samuel</hi> dreſs up <hi>Saul</hi> with commendations, when he ſet him before the people! 1 Sam. 10. 24. <hi>And Samuel ſaid to all the people, ſee ye him whom the Lord hath choſen, that there is none like him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all the people. And all the people ſhouted and ſaid, God ſave the King.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt hath been pleaſed to inſpire the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> to indite a ſacred <hi>Poem</hi> to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. The 45. <hi>Pſalm</hi> contains nothing but matter of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comium,</hi> and commendations to <hi>dreſs up the Crown,</hi> and the perſon of the <hi>Prince</hi> that wears it. If you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the <hi>Fifth</hi> Commandment, it enjoyns you to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour this your <hi>Civil Father,</hi> and he that <hi>uncovers his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſs</hi> to his reproach, the <hi>curſe</hi> of God, firſt or laſt, will light upon him. If <hi>Princes</hi> are not to be flattered, they are much leſs to be revil'd. Commendations, which may ſeem flattery, may be hanſome inſinuations and admonitions unto duty: but they are ſtigmatized for wicked men by two of the Apoſtles, who <hi>deſpiſe Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:168884:11"/> 
                  <hi>and ſpeak evil of Dignities.</hi> Saint <hi>Peter</hi> wonders at <note place="margin">2 Pet. 2. 10 Jude v. 8.</note> ſuch mens impudence, that <hi>they are not afraid to do ſo,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10. And well might they be afraid, had they not hearts of <hi>Adamant,</hi> as well as foreheads of <hi>Braſs;</hi> for <hi>Abiſhai</hi> thought the crime ſo hainous, that he ſhould do but a piece of juſtice, in <hi>ſtriking off the head of that dead dog,</hi> that barked in a railing language againſt his <note place="margin">2 Sam. 16. 9.</note> Soveraign; and the very pretence that he had blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med God and the King, coſt the precious life of <hi>Naboth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Laws are ſtrict enough in this point, if men had but the Conſcience to execute and obſerve them. And the Law of God is very ſevere too. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſpeak</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 22. 27. Act. 23. 5. Eccl. 10. 20</note> 
                  <hi>evil of the Ruler of the people,</hi> ſaith the Lord; And, <hi>is it fit to ſay to a King thou art wicked, and to Princes you are ungodly,</hi> ſaith <hi>Elihu,</hi> Job 34. 18. <hi>Curſe not the King, no not in thy thought,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But we have railing <hi>Shimei's,</hi> whoſe tongues are <hi>ſpears</hi> and <hi>arrows, ſwords</hi> and <hi>raſors,</hi> full of <hi>deadly poyſons,</hi> and <hi>ſet on fire of Hell;</hi> They durſt do that againſt their dread Soveraign, which the Arch-Angel durſt not do againſt the Prince of <hi>Devils.</hi> They <hi>durſt bring againſt him</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <note place="margin">Jude v. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>rayling accuſations.</hi> Theſe are your godly men, of the late Edition; though Saint <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>if any man ſeemeth to be religious, and bridleth not his tongue, this mans Religion is vain,</hi> James 1. 26.</p>
               <p>But it hath been the practiſe of theſe men, to go a gleaning in the holy Scriptures, and ſhutting their eys againſt the light of clear and expreſs commands, they retire into the ſhades of obſcure Propheſies, and ſerve their baſe and unworthy ends out of ſuch dark paſſages as they underſtand not (for did they underſtand them, they would know, they ſignifie nothing to their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. Out of this <hi>Quarry,</hi> they pick up ſtones to throw at the <hi>Crown,</hi> and dazle the Authority of their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:168884:12"/>
               <p> I inſiſt the longer upon this, becauſe <hi>Rebellion,</hi> which is as <hi>the ſin of Witchcraft,</hi> uſe to begin as Witchcraft doth in <hi>mutterings</hi> and <hi>murmerings</hi> of the lips, and the <hi>Prince</hi> is wounded firſt in <hi>Pulpits,</hi> and <hi>Pamphlets,</hi> and <hi>Corners,</hi> ever murthered by the <hi>tongue</hi> in his <hi>Reputation,</hi> before he is murdered by the <hi>Ax</hi> or <hi>Dagger</hi> in his <hi>Perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And let no man think to excuſe this inſolence, by al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, that ſome of the Prophets did make bold with the Majeſty of ſome Princes; For were thoſe Princes never ſo notoriouſly wicked, thoſe Prophets did, ſin if they had not a ſpecial and immediate commiſſion, to reprove them in ſuch rude language; And therefore Saint <hi>Paul</hi> convented before a perſon cloathed with Authority, becauſe he had called him <hi>whited Wall,</hi> and threatned that God ſhould <hi>ſmite him;</hi> upon admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he recants <hi>his raſhneſs,</hi> and condemns himſelf by a ſentence of holy Scripture, and is ſorry for his error, <hi>Act.</hi> 23. 5. For the <hi>Crown</hi> of Authority is not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſed with foul language: but to be <hi>dreſt up</hi> with <hi>lauds</hi> and acclamations to the perſon of the Prince.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It is to be <hi>dreſt up</hi> alſo by <hi>praiſes</hi> and <hi>thankſgivings</hi> rendred to Almighty God on the Kings behalf. For this we have an Apoſtolical exhortation, in the place foremention, <hi>I exhort that ſupplication and thankſgivings too be made for Kings,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 1, 2. And the holy Ghoſt hath prompted another Divine <hi>Poem</hi> to be penn'd for ſuch occaſions. <hi>The King ſhall rejoyce in thy ſtrength, O Lord,</hi> ſo that 21. <hi>Pſalm</hi> begins, and the concluſion is this, <hi>Be thou exalted, Lord, in thine own ſtrength: ſo will we ſing and praiſe thy power.</hi> And doubtleſs ſuch as under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and value ſo great a bleſſing, will heartily bleſs God for it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You muſt dreſs it up with an honourable <hi>Militia. Solomons</hi> Throne was ſupported by Lions; and he ſaith, <hi>the Throne is upheld by Judgment,</hi> taking the word in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:168884:12"/> ſevereſt ſenſe, when occaſion doth require it. Without a <hi>Militia</hi> (the Sword and a fair train of Artillery to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend and dreſs it up) the <hi>Crown</hi> will ſtand but for a gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en Cypher; it may ſerve other mens ends, to ſwell the accounts of their ambition and avarice: but it can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther protect the beſt Loyalty from oppreſſion, nor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend its own juſt Rights from uſurpation and violence. The holy Ghoſt therefore, in that Celebration of the Kings Majeſty and Glory, calls upon him to ſecure his Title and Intereſt in this particular, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. 3. <hi>Gird thy ſword upon thy thigh, O thou most mighty: with thy Glory and thy Majesty. And in thy Majeſty ride proſperouſly, and thy right hand ſhall teach thee terrible things. Thine arrows are ſharp in the heart of the Kings enemies, whereby the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple fall under thee.</hi> Thus you ſee the <hi>Militia</hi> ſerves to dreſs up the Crown. And if it did not of right belong unto it, why ſhould St. <hi>Paul</hi> make the Prince the moſt immediate <hi>Sword-bearer</hi> of the Almighty, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 4. He therefore that is inveſted with the Crown, muſt have the Militia to adorn and guard it.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if you would have the Crown to <hi>flouriſh</hi> kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you muſt dreſs it up by a prompt and cheerful <hi>obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</hi> But for the moſt part, the Commands of our Prince goes againſt the hair with us; they beget doubts and ſcruples; nay, 'tis well if they be not entertained with murmurings and diſputings; as if we had never learned our duty to our Superiours by the rule of the Apoſtle, nor been taught by his ſpirit. For his injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction is this <hi>ſervants be obedient to them that are your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters according to the fleſh, with fear and trembling, in ſingle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Epheſ. 6. 5, 6, 7, 8. Coloſ. 3. 22 23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>of your heart, as unto Chriſt: not with eye ſervice, as men-pleaſers, but as the ſervants of Christ, doing the will of God</hi> (even in point of obedience to your Soveraign) <hi>from the heart: with good will doing ſervice, as to the Lord, and not to men: knowing that of the Lord ye ſhall receive the reward of</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:168884:13"/> 
                  <hi>the inheritance: for</hi> (even in this your civil obedien) <hi>ye ſerve the Lord Chriſt.</hi> And upon this account, how doth Saint <hi>Peter</hi> conjure us to a dutiful ſubjection and obedience; <hi>Submit your ſelves, even for the Lords ſake, to the King as Supreme, and to them that are commiſſioned under him</hi> to rule over you, 1 Pet. 2. 13. And perhaps (as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> hath it) the people <hi>will be willing in the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 110. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>day of the Kings power.</hi> If not the Crown is obliged to ſecure its own glory, as well as Gods, with the wellfare of Church and State. And to this end, it was a juſt ſanction, that <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> inſerted into the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Ezra,</hi> in theſe words, <hi>And whoſoever will not do the Law of thy God and the Law of the King, let judgment be executed ſpeedily upon him, whether it be unto death, or to baniſhment, or to confiſcation of Goods, or to impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> Ezra 7. 26. But I muſt tell you, were there not a neceſſity of ſuch proceedings to ſecure the publick <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>order,</hi> it would be a <hi>tarniſhing</hi> of the Crown to have it thus garniſhed; I do rather therefore beſeech you to <hi>honour</hi> it by a <hi>free obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And yet I am afraid there are ſome, that (were it in their power) would be ready to dreſs up the Crown with more <hi>thorns</hi> and <hi>croſſes,</hi> inſtead of yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their dutiful aſſiſtance to make it <hi>flouriſh;</hi> ſome that would yet <hi>clip</hi> and <hi>waſh</hi> it, and uſe other of the late artifices to extract more gold out of it to varniſh and guild over their own crimes and fortunes. And yet I am loath to entertain ſo uncharitable a thought of ſuch men, as are under a <hi>ſolemn Vow and Covenant,</hi> whereby they have engaged themſelves <hi>with hands lifted up to heaven,</hi> to preſerve the <hi>Honour and Dignity of the Crown,</hi> and profeſs to approve themſelves <hi>His Majeſties beſt Subjects.</hi> I am unwilling to believe, that any of theſe men will <hi>invade the Rights of the Crown</hi> for their own advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Sure, they will never retain thoſe <hi>Lands</hi> in their
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:168884:13"/> own poſſeſſion that were deſigned and appropriated to bring forth fruits <hi>to dreſs up the Crown and make it flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi> Godly and well affected perſons, I grant, might make Purchaſes of ſuch Lands, to ſecure the Crowns intereſt, againſt God ſhould vouchſafe an opportunity for its Reſtitution: but who can think ſo hardly of any tender Conſcience, that it will defile it ſelf with ſuch an execrable ſacriledge and perjury as will attend the alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of thoſe Lands. No, no, perſons of integrity to their King and Country, if they keep any of thoſe Lands, 'tis to turn them all into <hi>Mines of Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,</hi> into <hi>Ore</hi> or <hi>Bullion,</hi> that reſcuing the Crown from ſo mean a thing as common earth, they may render it more glorious by a more refined and opulent Revenue. And indeed what loyal heart will not be ready to do as much to adorn the Crown, as <hi>Megpiboſheth</hi> offered to gratifie the avarice of a Sycophant upon the like oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, and ſay, Let the Crown <hi>take all</hi> (at leaſt all its dues) <hi>foraſmuch as my Lord the King is come again in peace</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 19. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>unto his own houſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>III. <hi>The third general Part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And <hi>my Lord the King</hi> is the perſon to whom of right the Crown belongeth; 'tis <hi>His Crown.</hi> And we muſt needs make ſome Reflexions upon this moſt <hi>excellent Perſon;</hi> A perſon not trained up in a trade of <hi>brewing—</hi>miſchief, againſt an opportunity ſhould offer it ſelf, to ſet the veſſel abroach, and vent it abroad to <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicate</hi> the Kingdom with rage, fury, and confuſion, not a perſon ſtudied in the Arts of <hi>Adulation</hi> and <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie,</hi> to ſeduce the hearts of the ſimple, to withdraw them from their <hi>allegiance,</hi> and tempt them into a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168884:14"/> to <hi>murder</hi> their lawful Soveraign, that he <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> may <hi>ſeize upon his inheritance.</hi> No, this is a Prince, <hi>the right and lawful Heir</hi> and Succeſſor himſelf, extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted out of the Loins of ſuch a Father of bleſſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as was the glory of his Church &amp; Kingdom, though the ſhame and confuſion of his enemies. And <hi>bleſſed art thou O Land, when thy King is the ſon of Nobles,</hi> Eccleſ. 10. 17. The Prince that owes this Crown, hath running in his veins the blood of that <hi>Royal Martyr,</hi> who ſealed to the truth of that <hi>Maxime</hi> by his ſufferings, whereof other Kings made but a complement; <hi>Salus populi Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prema Lex.</hi> He verified it by his death on that account, that the welfare of Church and State were his ſupream Law. And that pious ſacrifice did hallow the conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cration of this Prince to his Throne. A Prince <hi>preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved</hi> by a ſpecial providence, and I ſhould not miſcall it if I ſaid a miracle, from the <hi>malignant Sword,</hi> as that ſword is ſtiled by the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> which is drawn againſt the Lords <hi>Anointed.</hi> This is a Prince inſpired by the moſt incomparable diſcourſes of his Renowned Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <note place="margin">Pſal. 144. 10. Edit. Vulg.</note> with all the methods of prudence fit to inſtruct and furniſh the wiſeſt and beſt of Governors; and trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned up by a better Tutor too, in the <hi>School of Adverſity,</hi> where he hath learned to govern with prudence and moderation, even <hi>by the things which he hath ſuffered.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is a <hi>Character</hi> written of this Prince, a very ſhort and full one, which I deſire you all to buy and ſtudy, and as far as you are capable to imitate. If that does not give you ſatisfaction, touching the <hi>Heroick</hi> Vertues of this Prince; for my part, I ſhall not pretend to it: But if you ſeriouſly peruſe <hi>that,</hi> I think you muſt needs conclude with me, that were all the Crowns of <hi>Europe</hi> embroidered upon one Scarff, or melted down into one <hi>Diadem,</hi> with this motto, <hi>Detur Digniori,</hi> the merits of this Prince would entitle His Majeſty to ſtand
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168884:14"/> in competition for it againſt all Princes under heaven. This Prince, as if he had been ſent amongſt us for ſome ſignal bleſſing, was uſhered into the world at his birth, by a <hi>ſtar</hi> from heaven, and without all queſtion it was ſome ſpecial light from heaven that directed the <hi>wiſeſt</hi> men of thoſe Nations to addreſs themſelves to him, as the only Inſtrument of Gods deſignation, to redeem us from our long intollerable bondage. This was that ſtone (and there needs no more to be ſaid in his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations, than that this was He) which <hi>the builders of Babel</hi> amongſt us had <hi>refuſed,</hi> but is now become <hi>the head ſtone of the Corner</hi> to ſupport and unite us. <hi>This is the Lords</hi> (only) <hi>doing, and it is marvellous in our eyes.</hi> So that we may, in his Majeſties Name, ſhut up this with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21. 1, 2, 3. <hi>The King ſhall rejoyce in thy ſtrength O Lord: exceeding glad ſhall he be of thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Thou haſt given him his hearts deſire: and hast not denied him the requeſt of his lips. For thou preventeſt him with the bleſſings of goodneſs: and ſhall ſet a Crown of pure Gold upon his Head.</hi> And if God ſets the Crown <hi>there,</hi> we need not doubt our Text will have a full and happy accompliſhment, <hi>upon Himſelf ſhall his Crown flouriſh.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>IV. <hi>The fourth General part.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon Himſelf]</hi> But will <hi>Himſelf</hi> or <hi>His Crown,</hi> like that dead Sea, our late inſatiable gulf of <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> ſwallow up all our treaſure that is caſt into it to <hi>water</hi> it, and return us nothing in lieu of it, but oppreſsion and tyranny, wars, blood, and confuſion? There is no fear of that: the Crown hath <hi>vents</hi> enough to let out all you caſt in to water it, or apply to dreſs it up, and will return it back again upon you; and return it not ſuch
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168884:15"/> as it was when you caſt it in, but it will take a ſacred <hi>tincture</hi> from the Crown, and flow back upon you with ſufficient <hi>intereſt,</hi> with bleſſings and glorious advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Upon Himſelf:</hi> that is, upon you; for in a <hi>politick ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity</hi> the Prince and people make but one <hi>Body;</hi> he is the <hi>Head,</hi> they are the <hi>Members;</hi> So that while the Crown flouriſh upon <hi>Himſelf,</hi> the rayes of its ſplendor and beauty do reflect upon us, and adorn us all.</p>
               <p>This obſervation repreſents the <hi>union</hi> and <hi>endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> that ſhould be betwixt <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> as <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Members.</hi> But let no ſeditious miſcreant abuſe it to divide <hi>them,</hi> and ſet the <hi>law of the Members</hi> in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the <hi>law of the Mind,</hi> in the Supream Governor. For in this ſenſe 'tis a diſtinction forged in Hel, to teach men to reconcile Rebellion with obedience, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them they may deſtroy the <hi>natural perſon</hi> of their Prince, and yet be ſaved harmleſs from the <hi>Treaſon,</hi> by the charms of a <hi>politick capacity;</hi> and ſo 'tis deſigned to defeat the ſeverity of the Apoſtles intermination, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. <hi>They that reſiſt ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To return from this digreſſion. If the Crown flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh upon <hi>Himſelf,</hi> the influences thereof will make all things flouriſh under it. The <hi>Gentry</hi> will flouriſh, and the <hi>Prieſthood</hi> will flouriſh, and the <hi>Commons</hi> will flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh; <note place="margin">See Pſal. 72. &amp; 132. verſ. 15. 16</note> 
                  <hi>Merchants</hi> and <hi>Tradeſmen, Artificers</hi> and <hi>Husband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and all will flouriſh; for there will be no break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of ſorraign forces, no leading into <hi>captivity</hi> by <hi>civil inſurrections,</hi> no more cauſe of <hi>complaining in our ſtreets.</hi> And which is beſt of all, <hi>in his time the righteous ſhall flouriſh,</hi> and Religion ſhall flouriſh; for the <hi>Croſs</hi> of Chriſt never <hi>Triumphs</hi> ſo gloriouſly, as when it is advanced upon the Crowns of pious Princes. <hi>Truth ſhall flouriſh out of the earth, and Righteouſneſs ſhall look down from Heaven: Mercy and Truth will meet together, Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:168884:15"/> 
                  <hi>and Peace will kiſs each other.</hi> The Sun of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs will ſmile upon us, and ſpread his ſoft wings over us to heal and ſhelter us.</p>
               <p>And by the flouriſhing of the Kings Crown upon <hi>Himſelf,</hi> the whole Kingdom will be <hi>Crowned.</hi> The Church will be crowned with Order and Devotion, the Country with plenty and contentment, the Cities with Wealth, the Univerſities with Learning; all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions will be crowned with privileges, and the whole Nation with happineſs, peace, and glory. Theſe are the bleſſings we are to proclaim to you this day under the Authority of our moſt Gracious Soveraign.</p>
               <p>And yet I am unwilling to precipitate any backward inclinations to tranſact an affair of ſo great importance. Are you not hereby invited to oblige your ſelves to a huge piece of modern injuſtice, of <hi>rendring unto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, and to God the things that are Gods.</hi> Shall you not commit your ſelves priſoners to golden ſetters, by owning and ſubmitting to this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority? Will you not loſe the happineſs of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and that great priviledge, for every man <hi>to do what is right in his own eyes?</hi> Will not this be a return to your bounden duty and ſervice, and ſo cancel thoſe ſeveral <hi>late Oaths and Engagements,</hi> which have ſo long ſtood at <hi>Puſh-a-Pike</hi> one againſt another? Will you not return into the Sacred Canon, thoſe many Monarchical Texts of Scripture, which have ſo long been laid aſide as <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chryphal?</hi> ſhall you not run the hazard of being put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the influences of ſuch an <hi>ignorant, ſcandalous,</hi> or <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected Miniſtry</hi> as will grate your tender ears with the harſh Doctrines of <hi>loyalty</hi> and <hi>obedience;</hi> ſuch as will not have conſciences wide enough to permit you to ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thoſe ſweet morſels of <hi>Sacriledge</hi> without a check; but wil enveigh againſt it as a crime to enrich your ſelvs with the ſpoils of Gods Houſe, and a crime of ſo great
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168884:16"/> a magnitude, that it is not to be expiated without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and reſtitution? And will not ſuch a Miniſtry be ready to preſs upon you the obſervation of thoſe <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolete</hi> rules of the Apoſtle, <hi>to have all things that</hi> apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to Gods worſhip and ſervice, <hi>done decently and in</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 14. 40.</note> 
                  <hi>order?</hi> Will you not betray tender conſciences by this means, and deprive them of their ſweet liberty (which they have ſo long taken) <hi>to deſpiſe Dominion, and ſpeak evil of Dignities,</hi> and to revile all perſons in <hi>Sacred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> under the Title of <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts? Will you not hereby give encouragement to have that intollerable yoak of bondage put upon them, of <hi>worſhipping God in the beauty of holineſs?</hi> And though a due tolleration be <note place="margin">Pſal. 96. 9.</note> allowed to tender Conſciences, will they not be apt to be allured and drawn in by the Loadſtone and the Charms of a Royal example, <hi>To ſerve the Lord with fear, and to rejoyce before him with reverence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe, I know, are ſome of your great fears and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies; <note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 11.</note> nay, your main objections; though perhaps you'l think fit to cloath them with more diſmal and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Epithets; and truly, if any of you be not able to ſatisfie your ſelves in theſe particulars, for my part, I ſhall never adviſe you, to <hi>wound</hi> ſuch Conſciences by preſenting your ſelves to aſſiſt in the accompliſhment of this undertaking.</p>
               <p>And for ſuch whoſe hearts the Lord hath touched with a ſenſe of loyalty, and their duty to his Anointed, I have but three words to add by way of requeſt to them, not to eclipſe or ſully the Glory of this happy Day, with any <hi>debauchery</hi> or <hi>intemperance;</hi> for in ſtead of <hi>dreſsing up</hi> the Crown, ſuch unworthy practiſes will <hi>ſtain</hi> the fair flowers of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And now give the King thy Judgments, O God, &amp;c. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:168884:16"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAg. 12. lin. 2. read, Monarchical Government to be the more excellent, p. 15. l. 31, <hi>cuſtodire</hi> for <hi>cuſtodiri.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
